Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is דף צדי טת,
daf Tzaddi Tet, 99. We're in the beginning, well we're starting, we
started yesterday the next פרק, perek, פרק טבול יום, Perek T’vul Yom,
and we pick up here where it says
רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. The line is about 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, about 13 lines down.
So the משנה Mishnah basically said that the rule was that if
you are able to eat, or actually no, we'll get to that
in a minute. If you were able to do the עבודה avodah
during the day, you get to, you're entitled to a portion of
the meat at night, and if not, not. With the one exception
being a בעל מום. ba'al mum. They learn it from the פסוק
pasuk הכהן המחטא אתה יאכלנה. HaKohen HaMechattei Otah Yochalennah. And with two
sort of exegetical moves. One is reading מחטא mechattei not meaning the
one who's personally done it, which is certainly פשט p'shat of the
פסוק, pasuk, but the one who is fit to do it. So
anybody who is fit to bring it during the day. And יאכלנה
yochalennah does not mean is permitted to eat, I mean פסוקים p'sukim
say כל זכר בכהנים יאכל אתה. kol zachar bakohanim yochal otah. So
here it's probably the פשט p'shat reading יאכלנה yochalennah means entitled to
eat, which is therefore means יחלקנה yechalkennah gets a portion of it,
is entitled. Okay so that's what we said. And the בעל מום
ba'al mum is an exception. We learn from an extra פסוק pasuk
of כל זכר kol zachar to be a little bit more inclusive.
What, why did we choose בעל מום? ba'al mum? The גמרא Gemara
says we chose בעל מום ba'al mum because even though they are
not fit at night to do the עבודה, avodah, they're completely excluded
from the עבודה avodah forever, as opposed to a person who's just
טמא tamei for the day, but at least during the time that
the עבודה avodah was done, they were more in the category. During
the time the עבודה avodah was done in the day, the בעל
מום ba'al mum as opposed to the טמא tamei person was at
least able to be eating from the meat. And we're going to
there now sort of have some discussion that's going to focus us
on that, on the importance of being able to eat actually when
the עבודה avodah is being done, as opposed to necessarily the importance
of being able to do the עבודה. avodah. So now we're stressing
the ability to do the עבודה avodah when the עבודה avodah is
being done gives you a portion, but the בעל מום ba'al mum
who can never do the עבודה avodah is included because at least
then he was able to eat. Okay let's take a look now
the גמרא Gemara continues and it says רב יוסף אמר. Rav Yosef
amar. Now רב יוסף Rav Yosef is going to actually make this
point about why the בעל מום ba'al mum is more included, not
just because of the verse of כל זכר. kol zachar. רב יוסף
Rav Yosef says מכדי, michti, let's take a look. Line starts with
מכדי michti about 14 lines down. Let's take a look. מאי יאכלנה
יחלקנה. Mai yochalennah yechalkennah. We've just decided that the word יאכלנה yochalennah
means not just is permitted to eat, but is entitled to eat,
gets a portion. ליכתב רחמנא יחלקנה. Lichtav rachmana yechalkennah. So why did,
why didn't the פסוק pasuk say will get a portion? Why did
the פסוק pasuk say it in this vaguer way of
will eat? מאי יאכלנה, Mai yochalennah, why therefore did he choose to
express it in will eat as opposed to will get a portion?
שמע מינה ראוי לאכילה חולק שאינו ראוי לאכילה אינו חולק. Shema mina
ra'uy l'achilah cholek she'eino ra'uy l'achilah eino cholek. To tell you that
really the critical point here is not when the עבודה avodah was
being done were you able to do the עבודה, avodah, the critical
point that it's telling you is, since it's telling you who is,
that the entitlement to a portion and it's using the word of
the entitlement as יאכלנה, yochalennah, it's telling you that what entitles you
to a portion that night was your ability to eat during the
day. So although the verse says, right, because again, the focus here
is that a בעל מום ba'al mum can eat at all times.
He can never do the עבודה. avodah. So the פסוק pasuk says
הכהן המחטא אתה יאכלנה, HaKohen HaMechattei Otah Yochalennah, right, so we say
יאכלנה yochalennah means entitled and therefore we mean gets a חלק. chelek.
Okay so we've been assuming that who gets a חלק? chelek?
The מחטא, mechattei, one who is able to do the עבודה. avodah.
Ah we got בעל מום, ba'al mum, בעל מום ba'al mum isn't
able to do the עבודה. avodah. All right we got some פסוק
pasuk to throw him in. Okay and at least he's a little
bit connected because he could eat. But still the focus is able
to do the עבודה. avodah. Comes רב יוסף Rav Yosef and רב
יוסף Rav Yosef says uh-uh, maybe this means that we look at
the time of the עבודה, avodah, okay רב יוסף Rav Yosef says
no, you look at the time of the עבודה avodah but the
focus is יאכלנה, yochalennah, were you fit to eat at the time
of the עבודה? avodah? Okay since the word we're using here is
eat, not יחלקנה, yechalkennah, that really tells us the key consideration is
not were you able to do the עבודה avodah at the time
of the עבודה, avodah, but were you able to eat at the
time of the עבודה. avodah. We sort of much more bracketing מחטא.
mechattei. And therefore it's not like בעל מום ba'al mum is an
exception, it's actually you got the rule wrong. The rule isn't were
you able to do the עבודה avodah which is actually what the
משנה Mishnah says, and משנה Mishnah says כל שאינו ראוי לעבודה, kol
she'eino ra'uy l'avodah, but רב יוסף Rav Yosef really wants us to
do is he wants us to a little bit reorient and say
it's really more about were you able to eat during the time
of the עבודה. avodah. But how do you know he was able
to eat? That's a פסוק pasuk by בעל מום. ba'al mum. Right
but that's the same thing, both of them go back to that
same פסוק pasuk for בעל מום ba'al mum from כל זכר בכהנים.
kol zachar bakohanim. No, no, it's an explicit פסוק pasuk by the
בעל מום ba'al mum אך מקדשים יאכל ואל המזבח לא
יגש. ach me'kodashim yochal v'el hamizbe'ach lo yigash. Okay so the גמרא
Gemara says so now the גמרא Gemara says.
So we're going to focus on רב יוסף's Rav Yosef point. Is
the key that you were able to do the עבודה avodah at
the time of the עבודה avodah or is the key that you
were able to eat at the time of the עבודה? avodah? No,
he's not the conclusion, just the method of arrival. Yeah, but it
has implications as we're about to see. שמע מינה ראוי לאכילה חולק
שאינו ראוי לאכילה אינו חולק. Sh'ma mina ra'uy l'achilah cholek she'eino ra'uy
l'achilah eino cholek. By ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
asked. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is going to work with the old
assumption that בעל מום ba'al mum is an exception to the rule.
בעל מום ba'al mum והוא טמא. v'hu tamei. Somebody who was a
בעל מום, ba'al mum, started the day as a בעל מום, ba'al
mum, I mean you're going to end the day as a בעל
מום ba'al mum too. This guy's got a permanent מום mum and
in the middle of the day became טמא. tamei. Okay, and then
they brought a קרבן. korban. מהו שיחלקו לו? Ma'u she'yechalku lo? Do
you, can you,
are you entitled to a portion that night of the קרבנות korbanot
that were brought when you were טמא? tamei? Do we say כיון
דלא חזי ורחמנא רבייה? keivan d'lo chazi v'rachmana rabyei? Listen, as a
בעל מום ba'al mum you weren't fit to do the עבודה, avodah,
but you got a pass. The תורה Torah basically said we're going
to let you eat even though you weren't fit for the עבודה
avodah or we're going to give you a portion even though you
weren't fit for the עבודה. avodah. So you know what? Once you
get a pass for one thing, maybe you can piggyback on that
and get a pass for another thing. It's a pretty wild idea.
Okay, so it's not that the תורה Torah is bracketing the fact
that you're a בעל מום, ba'al mum, the תורה Torah is acknowledging
that you weren't ראוי לעבודה ra'uy l'avodah and saying nevertheless you're allowed
to eat. So once you're going through the day with a special
get out of jail free card, with a special permission to eat
to get a portion even though you're not fit, let's use that
permission even though you become a בעל מום. ba'al mum. One minute.
כיון דלא חזי ורחמנא רבייה לא שנא מה לי טמא מה לי
בעל מום. Keivan d'lo chazi v'rachmana rabyei lo shena ma li tamei
ma li ba'al mum. Okay, so you as a בעל מום ba'al
mum always have this get out of jail free card, this I'm
entitled to a portion even though I'm a בעל מום. ba'al mum.
So use that card even if you became טמא. tamei. או דלמא,
O dilma, or do we say no, שמע מינה ראוי לאכילה חולק
שאינו ראוי לאכילה אינו חולק? sh'ma mina ra'uy l'achilah cholek she'eino ra'uy
l'achilah eino cholek? At the end of the day, it's really, this
is really like the רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. Here he's effectively asking
the question of רב יוסף's Rav Yosef approach or the other approach.
If the approach is you really shouldn't be getting a portion but
we're making an exception in your case, so maybe that exception, maybe
that I'm still entitled to a portion, I got a special permission,
maybe that you could use to apply to other things, to being
טמא. tamei. But if we say like רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, there's
no exception. If we say like רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, we didn't
make a special permission for you. The question wasn't whether you could
do the עבודה, avodah, the question was whether you were able to
eat. As a בעל מום ba'al mum you were able to eat,
as a טמא tamei person you weren't able to eat. You got
it? So the question here makes it different. Do we see a
בעל מום ba'al mum as violating the rule and he's given special
exception and then maybe he can piggyback on that? Or do we
see no, no, no, the rule is were you able to eat
or not? Okay, so that, and therefore בעל מום ba'al mum isn't
an exception, we just have to reorient ourselves, understand really what the
rule is. Now of course, if this was an exception, there's no
logic to think that you could piggyback this, you know, another problem
on top of this
exception, okay? But at least we're opening up to that question if
you view this as a type of an exception. So let's see
what the גמרא's Gemara answer
is. אמר רבה תא שמע, Amar Rabbah ta sh'ma, come and hear.
כהן גדול מקריב אונן ואינו אוכל ואינו חולק לאכול לערב. Kohen gadol
makriv onen v'eino ochel v'eino cholek l'echol la'erev. So this is a
great proof to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. There are actually people who
are entitled, we've been so assuming that, you know, if you can't
do the עבודה avodah you can't eat and, you know, maybe there's
a בעל מום ba'al mum who can't do the עבודה avodah and
he can eat and we were assuming that of course anybody who
can't do the עבודה avodah can't eat. But actually it's not, I'm
sorry, I got that wrong, because a בעל מום ba'al mum can
eat. We were assuming that anybody who can't eat, excuse me, certainly
can't do the עבודה, avodah, right? Because a טמא tamei person can't
eat, can't do the עבודה. avodah. A בעל מום ba'al mum can
eat and do the עבודה, avodah, wait, a בעל מום ba'al mum
can eat and do—no, a בעל מום ba'al mum can eat and
not do the עבודה. avodah. But anybody who can't eat, certainly can't
do the עבודה. avodah. It says no, there are people actually who
can't eat and who can do the עבודה. avodah. Who can't eat
and can do the עבודה? avodah? Well, a כהן גדול kohen gadol
who's an אונן. onen. I bet that would have been the first
thing that would have occurred to you. Because the הלכה halachah is
a כהן גדול kohen gadol who's an אונן, onen, the פסוק pasuk
says ומן המקדש לא יצא, u'min hamikdash lo yeitzei, right? Don't leave
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash even if, you know, an immediate relative
died. Okay, so he is told that he stays in the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but nevertheless that is to enable him to do
the continue to do the עבודה. avodah. Eating, which is not an
act of the עבודה avodah per se, because he's an אונן, onen,
he's not allowed to eat. So you have a, so now you've
got this כהן גדול. kohen gadol. He's doing the עבודה avodah today.
He's an אונן. onen. He brought this שלמים. shelamim. He brought this
חטאת. chatas. He's able to do the עבודה, avodah, he did the
עבודה. avodah. Does he get a portion of that שלמים shelamim and
חטאת chatas at night? Do we say if the rule is were
you able to do the עבודה avodah and then he does get
a portion that night because that night his אונן onen status goes
away? Or do we say even though you did the עבודה, avodah,
you weren't able to eat and it's all about your ability to
eat which entitles you to a portion? Okay, so
that, you got the question? So this is a perfect way of
asking what's it really about, your entitlement, your getting a portion at
the night? Was it the fact that you were able to do
the עבודה avodah or was it the fact that you were able
to eat? So a כהן גדול אונן kohen gadol onen is a
great example. He was able to do the עבודה avodah and not
able to eat. He's the exact flip of the בעל מום. ba'al
mum. Okay.
כהן גדול מקריב אונן, Kohen gadol makriv onen, he brings his קרבנות
korbanot when he's an אונן onen and he's not. ואינו אוכל, ve'eino
ochel, he's not entitled to eat as an אונן, onen, ואינו חולק
לאכול לערב, ve'eino cholek leachol la'erev, and he doesn't get a portion.
So it's not enough that you were able to do the עבודה.
avoda. It's all about, were you able to eat? So כהן גדול
אונן kohen gadol onen and a בעל מום baal mum are two
sides of the same coin, right? בעל מום baal mum can eat
and not do the עבודה, avoda, כהן גדול kohen gadol can do
the עבודה avoda and not eat, and the answer is for both
of them, it all depends on whether you were able to eat.
A בעל מום baal mum is more included than a כהן גדול
אונן, kohen gadol onen, and it's not because a בעל מום baal
mum is an exception, it's because the key question is, were you
able to eat when the עבודה avoda was being done? שמע מינה
ראוי לאכילה בעינן שמע מינה. shma mina rauy leachila beinan shma mina.
So this is a great proof to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, and
it therefore answers our other question: just because you're a בעל מום,
baal mum, you don't eat because you're also טמא. tamei. A בעל
מום... baal mum... there's not an exception to a בעל מום baal
mum with a special permission, okay? It has nothing to do, בעל
מום baal mum is not... we don't make an exception for him.
The real principle is whether you were fit to eat. So בעל
מום, baal mum, yes, gets a portion, כהן גדול אונן, kohen gadol
onen, no, and a בעל מום baal mum who is טמא, tamei,
the answer is no. We don't make an exception for a בעל
מום. baal mum. If you were טמא, tamei, then you weren't able
to eat, so you're not going to get a portion. Yes, Michael?
So what's interesting is, you know, I would have thought that, you
know, the בעל מום, baal mum, him being a בעל מום, baal
mum, because you know, he has to go from wherever it is,
right? Is it just that he just came? Or are the בעלי
מומים baalei mumim expected to go for the משמרות mishmarot and just
be there? And then, you know, eat if someone gives it to
them, you know... Yeah, well, it's not someone gives it to them.
Meaning that they get... he does get a portion. Right, no, fine.
Meaning but so he can go into the עזרה? azara? Yeah, yeah.
And so are they expected to show up just to get their
חלק? chelek? No, that's a good question. When it's the משמר mishmar
and somebody's a בעל מום, baal mum, I mean, it's free meat
for the, you know, why not? You're going to get a lot
of meat if you're a בעל מום. baal mum. No, but is
he actually... is he expected to go? I don't know, that's a
good question. Would they have other things for the בעלי מומים baalei
mumim to do? I'm trying to think that there is... Can he
like peel the, you know, de-worm the wood or something? Yeah, yeah,
yeah, he could. So I don't know, it's a good question. They
probably would have particular things that other people wouldn't want to be
doing that the בעל מום baal mum could do. Yeah, but it's
a good point. I'm assuming that they were expected to go, but
you're right, it's a good question. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara
says like this: so now we're going to ask another question which
is just going to highlight the same fact point that we've made,
which is that it's about whether you're fit to eat, not whether
you're fit to do the עבודה. avoda. So really, it shifts the
כלל klal that we came... that the משנה mishnah said, but it
allows the בעל מום baal mum not to be an exception, it
allows him to just fit the rule. Okay, בעי רב הושעיא. ba'i
Rav Oshaya. רב הושעיא Rav Oshaya asked: טמא בקרבנות ציבור מהו שיחלקו
לו? tamei bekorbanos tzibur mahu sheyechalku lo? Okay,
here's a good question. Okay, it was a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur
and, and you were טמא tamei today. Okay, but... and it's a
little bit of a funny question because had the majority of כהנים
kohanim been טמא tamei or whatever, then you would have been allowed
to have brought the קרבן ציבור korban tzibur even though you're טמא.
tamei. Okay? So you're considered to be fit. רש"י Rashi says that
it was actually brought today by the טהורים. tehorim. You could say
that no, it actually was brought by טמא tamei people today, okay?
But anyway, the point is you're fit to do the עבודה. avoda.
But even when a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur is brought בטומאה, betuma,
it's not נאכל בטומאה, ne'echal betuma, okay? So it's not going to
be... so it's only able to be eaten by טהור tehor people
because the focus of the override, it's sort of like the כהן
גדול אונן, kohen gadol onen, the focus of the override is to
allow it to be brought. We don't... it's not so critical whether
it's eaten or not, and therefore we don't override the טומאה tuma
consideration for it to be eaten, okay? So this case is where
it's brought, you're able to bring it, at least in theory, but
you're not able to eat it. And then by night, you're no
longer טמא. tamei. Are you entitled to a
portion? טמא בקרבנות ציבור מהו שיחלקו לו? tamei bekorbanos tzibur mahu sheyechalku
lo? Do we divide for him? מי אמרינן, mi amrinan, do we
say המחטא אמר רחמנא והאי נמי מחטא הוא? hamchatei amar rachmana vehai
nami mechatei hu? He's in a principle of able to bring it,
even though you're טמא, tamei, it's a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur. או
דילמא, o dilma, do we say ראוי לאכילה חולק שאין ראוי לאכילה
אינו חולק? rauy leachila cholek she'ein rauy leachila eino cholek? It's not
really about whether you're able to bring it, it's whether you were
able to eat it. אמר רבינא תא שמע. amar Ravina ta shema.
רבינא Ravina said, come and hear. כהן גדול kohen gadol is the
perfect example. כהן גדול מקריב אונן ואינו אוכל ואינו חולק לאכול לערב.
kohen gadol makriv onen ve'eino ochel ve'eino cholek leachol la'erev. כהן גדול
kohen gadol brings, but he can't eat, because he can't eat he
doesn't get a portion that night, even though at night he can
eat, since he couldn't eat during the day. שמע מינה ראוי לאכילה
בעינן שמע מינה. shma mina rauy leachila beinan shma mina. So you
see it's perfect, everything fits the rules, there's no exceptions, okay? The
real key is not were you able to do the עבודה, avoda,
but at the time of the עבודה, avoda, were you able to
eat? And the answer for a בעל מום baal mum is yes,
so he gets a portion at night. The answer for a כהן
גדול אונן kohen gadol onen is no, he doesn't get a portion,
and the answer for a טמא tamei כהן kohen in קרבנות ציבור
korbanos tzibur is no, so he doesn't get a portion, okay? So
it all goes by
fit to be eaten... whether you were fit to eat it, and
there are no exceptions, at least not that we've seen so far.
Okay, now moving on to the משנה, mishnah, going to the אונן
onen focus, and this now we're going to get into, maybe דוקא
davka we could do the דף daf on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av
we'll have to see where we're up to because it's all about
אנינות, aninus, it's all about loss. Anyway, somebody's suffered a tragic loss.
We could learn this on תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. I would probably.
Anyway, so, so now we're going to get into a whole discussion
in the גמרא gemara where אנינות aninus gets discussed in a serious
way about אנינות aninus by קרבנות korbanos because our משנה mishnah says
that an אונן onen can touch קרבנות, korbanos, but he can't eat,
and because he can't eat eat again and can't do the עבודה
avodah *avoda* excluding a כהן גדול kohen gadol *kohen gadol*. Okay, since
so therefore he does not get a portion at night even though
presumably his אנינות aninus *aninus* is over at night, and this is
the general principle that if somebody suffered a loss that day and
buried the person that day or whatever or regardless, okay, the אנינות
aninus *aninus* status applies for the day in the תורה Torah *Torah*
and not at night. Now again, by אונן onen *onen* we often
mean different things. By אונן onen *onen* for us practical purposes we
mean questions like somebody is פטור patur *patur* in doing מצוות mitzvos
*mitzvos*. Certain restrictions apply to an אונן onen *onen* about eating meat
and drinking wine and so on. That's not what we're talking about
at all here. What we're talking about is actually that more technical
term is מתו מוטל לפניו *meto mutal lefanav*. Okay, אונן onen *onen*
here really is completely that sense of somebody who has immediately suffered
this tragic loss and therefore is excluded from the world of קרבנות
korbanos, *korbanot*. And that exclusion, the assumption here is applies on the
immediate day, not the following night. So our משנה Mishnah *mishna* says
that that אונן onen *onen* is allowed to touch קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*.
Is he allowed to touch? It doesn't say anything about it. Right,
well of course he is, but again, as you point out, there's
a whole concern by אונן onen. *onen* because of his involvement with
מת meis *met* or whatever. So that's exactly what we're going to
see. An אונן onen *onen* is allowed to touch, okay, but he
cannot bring and he can't eat, and therefore he doesn't get portions
that night. Okay, so really an אונן onen *onen* is completely excluded
during the time of the אנינות aninus *aninus* from bringing, from eating,
he's not going to get a portion. But the חידוש *chiddush* in
the משנה Mishnah. *mishna*, at least our גרסא *girsa* of the משנה
Mishnah *mishna*, there was a question, the חידוש *chiddush* in our משנה
Mishnah *mishna* at least, the whatever, seems to be that he is
allowed to touch קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot*. He's not טמא tamei, *tamei*. We're
not concerned that he's טמא tamei *tamei*. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. אונן onen נוגע ואינו מקריב *onen nogea ve'eino
makriv*. אונן onen נוגע *onen nogea*? Is an אונן onen *onen* really
allowed to touch? We're not concerned that he's טמא tamei *tamei*? Or
we haven't given him some rabbinic טומאה tumah *tumah*? ורמינהי uremini, *ureminihi*?
I'll ask you on this. We've got a משנה Mishnah. *mishna* in
חגיגה chagiga *Chagigah*. אונן onen ומחוסר כיפורים *onen umechusar kippurim*, an אונן
onen, *onen* and somebody who is waiting to bring his קרבן korban,
*korban* to be fit to become טהור tahor *tahor*, צריכים טבילה tvila
לקודש *tzrichim tvila lekodesh*. If they want to go ahead and eat
קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*, they need to immerse, okay? So you see that
an אונן onen *onen* is considered טמא tamei, *tamei*—meaning, and not just
eat, okay, טבילה לקודש *tzrichim tvila lekodesh* presumably means even touch קרבנות
korbanot *korbanot*. Okay, at least vis-a-vis קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*, he is considered
טמא tamei *tamei* and he needs to go to the מקוה mikvah,
*mikvah*. But doesn't everyone need טבילה *tvila* though to eat? Well, I
mean, if you're טהור tahor, *tahor* you don't. But all כהנים *kohanim*
when they serve they have to... That's to do the עבודה avodah
*avoda*. This is just to touch. We're not talking about doing the
עבודה avodah, *avoda*. We're not at this stage even think we're talking
about eating קרבנות korbanos, *korbanot*. We think we're just talking about touching.
We think that the basic point of this is that we presume
that an אונן onein *onen* is considered to be a low-level of
טומאה tumah, *tumah*, like a שלישי shlishi *shlishi*, okay, similar low-level of
טומאה tumah. *tumah* as a מחוסר כיפורים *mechusar kippurim*. And the only
effect that that low-level of טומאה tumah *tumah* has is if he
touches חולין chulin, *chullin* he won't make it טמא tamei *tamei*, if
he touches תרומה terumah, *terumah* he won't make it טמא tamei *tamei*,
but he can't touch a קרבן korban. *korban*, okay? It's the lowest
level of טומאה tumah *tumah* that it just keeps you away from
touching a קרבן korban. *korban* until you go to the מקוה mikvah
*mikvah*. So here it seems like at least רבנן *rabbanan*—right, obviously this
isn't a biblical טומאה tumah, *tumah* as being an אונן onein. *onen*—but
at least רבנן *rabbanan* we give him some level of טומאה tumah
*tumah* that he can't touch קרבנות korbanos *korbanot*. So how could our
משנה Mishnah. *mishna* say he could touch קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*? Okay. צריכים
טבילה לקודש *tzrichim tvila lekodesh*. אמר רב אמי אמר רבי יוחנן *amar
Rav Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan*, לא קשיא lo kashya, *lo kashya*, כאן
בשטבל כאן בשלא טבל *kan shetaval kan shelo taval*. No problem. Our
משנה Mishna *mishna* is talking that he already went to the מקוה
mikvah, *mikvah*. Okay? You're right, an אונן onein *onen* they gave an
אונן onen, *onen* a very low-level טומאה tumah *tumah* that he can't
touch קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*. Our משנה mishnah *mishna* that says he can
touch is talking that he went to the מקוה mikvah *mikvah*. Well,
that's an easy enough answer. Except that it isn't. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says וכי טבל מאי הוי *vechi taval mai hava*? Who
cares if he went to the מקוה mikvah *mikvah*? הדרא ליה אנינות
aninus *hadra lei aninus*. But he's still an אונן onen, *onen* today.
So he gets out of the מקוה mikvah *mikvah*, it's like טובל
ושרץ בידו *tovel vesheretz beyado*, טובל ואנינות בידו *tovel veaninus beyado*. You
go to the מקוה mikvah, *mikvah*, the guy's still an אונן onen
*onen*, so the טבילה *tvila* doesn't help. So when it says he
needs טבילה *tvila*, it means when the day is over and his
אנינות aninus *aninus* is over, then he needs to go, okay? And
that's an interesting question what it means by מחוסר כיפורים *mechusar kippurim*.
התוספות *Tosafot* has a whole discussion—does it mean after you bring your
קרבן korban, *korban* you still have to go to the מקוה mikvah
*mikvah*? Okay, but by אנינות aninus *aninus* it means after the guy's
אנינות aninus *aninus* is over that night, then he goes to the
מקוה mikvah *mikvah* and then he's okay. But he can't go to
the מקוה mikvah *mikvah* that day. So we're still back to the
problem. An אונן onen, *onen* should always be a problem touching קרבנות
korbanot. *korbanot*. דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אונן onen, שטבל אנינותו חוזרת
עליו *da'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana onen shetaval aninuto chozeret alav*. His
אנינות aninus *aninus* returns to him. It doesn't help. So we're back
to our question. It seems that an אונן onen *onen* can't touch
קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* and our משנה mishna *mishna* says an אונן onen
*onen* can. לא קשיא
*lo kashya*. It's not difficult. הא דאסיח דעתיה הא דלא אסיח דעתיה
*ha de'asiach da'ateih ha delo asiach da'ateih*. The question is, and this
is exactly what Michael was asking yesterday, is that an אונן onen
*onen* we think that he might stop watching himself and protecting himself
and paying, you know, sort of being vigilant that he does not
become טמא tamei *tamei*. And therefore we're afraid he touched טמא tamei
*tamei* things. Now why is this? So Michael says, well the guy
is so involved in burying, you know, the dead, so maybe he
touched—he touched actually, you know,
the father, the brother, the mother, the sister, whoever it is that
passed away. That's not exactly the concern. I mean, that might be
a concern, but the more immediate concern is that the אונן onen
*onen* says like okay,
I can't do עבודה avodah, *avoda*... in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
today, so, so
not I might like, like consciously become טמא, tamei but you stop
being so careful, right? I'm sort of, that's it, I'm not going
to be in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash today anyway, which raises
an interesting question. Why don't we assume that a בעל מום baal
mum is regularly טמא tamei or something like that? Okay, but maybe
that would be a little bit unfair, but אנינות aninus is a
one, you know, is a one-time acute type of thing. Okay. So
anyway, so, so, so
if he has הסח הדעת, hesach hadaas, if he stops paying attention,
that's when he's considered טמא tamei and that's when we'll say the
טומאה tumah goes back on him even if he goes to the
מקוה, mikvah etc., etc., etc. Our משנה mishna that says an אונן
onen can touch is a circumstance maybe by default we say an
אונן onen, we're treating them as טמא, tamei but if it's a,
but if an אונן onen we know and says I am being
super careful, etc., and it's clear that he is continuing to pay
attention, we would not consider him to be טמא tamei and that's
our משנה. mishnah, Okay. Or maybe just go to the מקוה mikvah
and we wouldn't say it comes back, not exactly clear where it's
landing on that. Okay. כאן בהסח הדעת הא דלא הסח הדעת. Kan
be'hesach hadaas, ha d'lo hesach hadaas. So the גמרא Gemara says,
הסח הדעת? hesach hadaas? Wait, if he stops paying attention to him
being careful, שלישי ושביעי בו. shelishi ve'shevii bo.
Then, now this really feeds into what Michael says, then we're concerned
he actually touched a dead body. Okay? It's not just we're concerned
he touched some שרץ. sheretz. Okay? Maybe again, maybe it's just we
go to the maximum concern. Maybe because he just lost somebody and
the corpse is right over there. Okay? So if he's really stopped
paying attention, that can't be the case where it says he has
to go to the מקוה, mikvah etc. Okay? Because then the מקוה
mikvah isn't enough. He needs to sprinkle on day three and
seven. דאמר רב יוסטאי בריה דרבי מתון אמר רבי יוחנן הסח הדעת
צריך הזיה שלישי ושביעי. D'amar Rav Yostai brei d'Rabbi Mattun amar Rabbi
Yochanan: Hesach hadaas tzarich hazayah shelishi ve'shevii. So we're stuck. If there
was הסח הדעת, hesach hadaas, מקוה mikvah isn't enough. Okay? So the
case of מקוה mikvah must be no הסח הדעת. hesach hadaas. And
then we're back to our question, which is so which, so where
is he allowed to touch? Okay? So לא
קשיא הא דאסח דעתיה מטומאת מת הא דאסח דעתיה מטומאת שרץ. Lo
kashya: Ha de'asach daatei mi'tumei meis, ha de'asach daatei mi'tumei sheretz. Okay.
So, so the גמרא Gemara. says like this. Ah, there's a, you
can have different degrees of how uncareful you're being. Okay? You could
say, look, it's true, you know, the guy could say, I realized
I wasn't going to be in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, today,
I stopped being so, so super careful. But I stopped being super
careful, I didn't stop being careful. Okay? So believe me, I still,
I'm a כהן kohen or whatever. I mean, especially if you think
that a כהן kohen is not allowed to become, well, I guess
if it's an immediate relative he's a מצוה mitzvah to become טמא
למת, tamei l'meis, but it doesn't matter. He says I would know
whether I'm becoming טמא tamei to a מת meis, or not. So
I can't promise you I was on my height of vigilance to
make sure I didn't touch like a corpse or a שרץ sheretz
or whatever, but trust me, I'm not a טמא מת, tamei meis,
that I was careful about. So now what we've got is these
different levels. Okay? You've got the אונן onen who is
הסח הדעת ממת, hesach hadaas mi'meis, okay, and whoops, ממת, mi'meis, he's
being completely careless and there he needs three and seven. Then you've
got the אונן onen that's הסח הדעת hesach hadaas sort of מטומאת
שרץ. mi'tumei sheretz. Okay? So that's like a, just a, just
not super careful. I am assuming that we're going to say that
that's probably the default, it's the sense one gets. Okay, this is
the default אונן. onen. Which, as I said, I heard that it
doesn't make sense Michael, but quiet, we first have to make sure
that everyone understands what it is before we decide whether it makes
sense. The default אונן onen is that you're not super careful but
you're not super uncareful. And that type of a person is considered
to be, okay, טמא tamei, for one day, like you know, for
the day, טמא tameh, for the day. Even if you go to
the מקוה, mikvah you still go back and you're still טמא tameh.
for the day. Okay, it doesn't help. Okay, that's this guy. And
then you have the case about no הסח הדעת hesach hadaas
which is, okay, this is, this is super careful
and this is
super careless.
Okay? And this guy is the default. Okay, so the משנה mishnah,
that says an אונן onen is טמא tameh, and then the clarification
that if he goes, presumably for the day, and if he goes
to the מקוה mikvah, it repeats, that's the default אונן onen that
has הסח הדעת hesach hadaas from שרץ. sheretz. The statement that if
you're a real הסח הדעת hesach hadaas is three and seven, we're
going to say is הסח הדעת hesach hadaas from a מת, met
okay? That's the super careless one. Our משנה mishnah that says that
an אונן onen can go ahead and touch קרבנות, korbanot that's a
super careful אונן onen and there he's either not טמא tameh. at
all, this isn't clear, or he's טמא tameh, but if you go
to the מקוה mikvah it won't resume. Okay? And that's our case
of our משנה. mishnah Okay, that's our משנה. mishnah Question? Yeah. So
that's a pretty nice structuring of
this. Assuming he's gone to the מקוה mikvah and it's still the
day, wouldn't he still be a
טבול יום? tevul yom? Yeah, but, oh, so that's a question about
whether, right, which is within the גמרא's Gemara answer that he went
during the day and does it חזרה עליו chozra alav or whatever,
right, right,
yes. But I mean a normal טבול יום tevul yom has a
higher level, the טבול יום tevul yom brings him down to a
שני. sheni. This guy sort of starts like a שלישי shlishi, or
whatever, so the טבילה might help immediately. That's also a similar question
by the מחוסר כפורים. mechusar kippurim. So that's what this big תוספות
Tosafot discusses. All right, so it's a good question, but maybe is
the answer. All right, so now let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara,
Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, והא הערב שמש באי, veha
haerev shemesh baee, one minute says the גמרא, Gemara in this case
where we're afraid you touched a שרץ, sheretz, okay,
if here when we're afraid that you weren't careful about a מת
met, we treat it as if you touched a מת, met, then
here when you're telling us you're not careful about שרץ, sheretz, we're
going to treat it as if you touched a שרץ. sheretz. Okay?
Then you need to go to the מקוה mikvah and wait for
nightfall. This is exactly Michoel's question, going to the מקוה immediately shouldn't
help. But I have to tell you, I did some research, I
didn't understand this question, because once we say אנינות חוזרת עליו, aninut
chozeret alav,
effectively we're saying that you know you need nightfall here, right? So
I'm not exactly sure, but it's a different model. Rather than saying
the מקוה worked but because you're still an אונן onen it comes
back, it's like so effectively the מקוה doesn't work. Okay, but anyway,
but that's one model. Yes, you went to the מקוה but it
came back. The other model is if we consider it as if
you touched a שרץ, sheretz, okay, then fundamentally going to the מקוה
isn't enough, you have to go to the מקוה and wait for
nightfall. So it all works out the same I think, but like
the model is different. Okay. Number one. So it does not seem
like we're concerned here that you touched a שרץ. sheretz. Number two,
ועוד אפילו תרומה נמי, veod afilu terumah nami, if we're concerned you
touched a שרץ, sheretz, then why are you not just allowed to
touch קרבנות, korbanot. you should not be allowed to touch even תרומה,
terumah. right? Because we said until now you are a שלישי, shlishi.
fine, that's rabbinic, that's a low level, we can give you that
level and say only קרבנות. korbanot But if we're afraid you touched
a שרץ, sheretz, you would be a שני. sheni. So you shouldn't
be allowed to touch even תרומה. terumah. So this category that the
אונן, onen the default אונן onen is טמא tameh, and that's not
the case of our משנה mishnah, or whatever, and you want to
say it's הסח הדעת, hesech hadaat, and הסח הדעת hesech hadaat means
we're concerned you touched a שרץ, sheretz, if that's really what it
is, not just a low level rabbinic טומאה, tumah, if it's something
that comes because you might have touched a שרץ, sheretz, then we
should be treating you like a שני sheni and you shouldn't be
allowed to touch תרומה. terumah. So let's take a look. אמר רבי
ירמיה בנטירותא לפלגא, amar Rabi Yirmiya benetiruta lepalga, so this is going
to get even more hairsplitting, נשמרתי מדבר המטמאני ולא נשמרתי מדבר הפוסלני.
nishmarti midevar hamatmeini velo nishmarti midevar haposleni.
So the guy said I was careful enough to make sure I
really didn't touch a שרץ, sheretz, nothing that would have made me
a שני, sheni, nothing that would have gotten me in trouble with
תרומה. trumah, I wasn't careful about possibly touching something that would have
made me a שלישי. shlishi? Now that is completely bizarre, because what
can you touch that would have made me a שלישי? shlishi, And
it's one thing to say I know I didn't touch a dead
body, I didn't go into a room with a corpse, right? It's
another thing to say, oh I was careful enough to make sure
I didn't touch a שרץ, sheretz, I wasn't careful enough, I was
sort of saying to myself is this a שני sheni or a
ראשון rishon or a שלישי, shlishi? I'll decide whether I'm going to
be careful about it or not. Like it's very bizarre that you
would be able, it's one thing to say I'm staying away from
dead bodies. It's another thing anyway. And what is that thing that
would have made you into a שלישי? shlishi. Okay, but that's now
the scenario that we're breaking it, that the case where you're only
אסור assur for
קדשים kodashim is a guy that was careful enough not to touch
a שרץ sheretz but not careful enough not to touch something that
would make him a שלישי. shlishi. So the גמרא Gemara says ומי
איכא נטירותא לפלגא, umi ika netiruta lepalga, can you really watch yourself
and split hairs that way? Again, it wasn't bothered about that about
corpses, but it is bothered about this about שני sheni versus שלישי.
shlishi Okay, אין והתניא, in vehanya, yes, I'll show you that we
can say that somebody can have a certain degree of care, such
a fine-tuned degree of care. Here's a ברייתא. braita. היה עוסק בסל
ובגרוגרות, hayah osek besal uvegrogerot, here you have a guy that is
picking dates or whatever or figs like these גרוגרות, grogerot, those are
figs, right? They're all smooshed together and he's got a סל sal
of the figs on his head and he's got like a מגרפה
magrefa or something he uses to like break up the figs, you
know, in the basket. ואמר לבי על הסל ואין לבי על המגרפה,
veamar libi al hasal veein libi al hamagrefa, I am paying attention
to the basket to make sure nothing טמא tamei, touches it, but
I am not paying attention to the shovel to make sure nothing
טמא tamei touches it. Okay. הסל טהור, hasal tahor, so then the
סל sal is טהור because he says he was careful, והמגרפה טמאה,
vehamagrefa tmeiah, and the מגרפה's magrefa טמאה tmeiah because he wasn't being
careful about it. Okay. We assume it became טמא, tamei, I mean,
yeah, whatever, so yes. Okay, let's not worry about that, but
yes. Okay. So now he says like this. Now, ותטמא המגריפה—now vetitmeh
hamagrefah the גמרא Gemara asks, but one minute, this logically doesn't make
sense: ותטמא מגריפה לסל. vetitmeh magrefah lasal. If the shovel is טמא,
tamei let the shovel be מטמא metameh the barrel. No, that's not
a question. אין כלי מטמא כלי. ein kli metameh kli. A כלי
kli is not מטמא כלי metameh kli because a כלי kli is
a ראשון. rishon. Okay, the general principle is that anything, the only
thing that can go lower than a ראשון, rishon, you know, other
than a person with some of these weird things like טבול יום,
tevul yom, but basically through contact, the only thing that can go
lower than a ראשון rishon is food. Okay, the basic principle here
is,
okay,
so you have the אב הטומאה av hatumah which is like the
אבי אבות, avi avos, right? Well, right, like the corpse, right, I
mean, whatever, that's the אבי אבות, avi avos, the מת, the נבילה,
nevelah, the זב, zav, whatever. Okay, you have the אב. av. Then
you have the ראשון rishon which touches the אב, av, right? This
is all through touch. Who can become a ראשון? rishon? אדם, adam,
כלים, keilim, and food. Then the ראשון rishon touches something else and
it becomes a שני. sheni. The only thing that can become a
שני sheni through touch, right again, a person through being a טבול
יום tevul yom or whatever, but the only thing through touch is
אוכל, ochel, is food. The only thing that can become a שלישי
shlishi. is תרומה, trumah which is a subset of food, okay? And
the only thing that can become a רביעי revii is קדשים. kodashim.
I mean, I guess here it's תרומה trumah, and קדשים. kodashim. Okay,
so from שני sheni on though, it's only foods, okay? And it's
turtles all the way down. Okay, so anyway, okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, so you're watching this basket with the dates and with
the figs and with the shovel, and we're afraid that the shovel
became טמא. But the basket's okay. Well, if the something got touched,
the shovel's a ראשון. rishon. So why isn't the shovel מטמא metameh
the basket? Because
a
basket, a כלי kli can't be מטמא כלי, metameh kli, but that
a basket can't become a שני. sheni. The shovel is a ראשון
rishon and a כלי kli can't become a שני. sheni. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara
says, אין כלי מטמא כלי. ein kli metameh kli. ותטמא מה שבתוכו?
vetitmeh mah shebetokho? Fine, but let the shovel be מטמא metameh the
figs? Because the ראשון rishon shovel can make the figs into a
שני. sheni. Okay, that's our question. ותטמא מה שבתוכו? vetitmeh mah shebetokho?
אמר רבא, amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, באומר שמרתיה מדבר מטמאה ולא
שמרתיה מדבר הפוסלה. be-omer shimartiha midavar metame'ah velo shimartiha midavar haposlah. Okay,
so here we're going to be, this is why we brought this
in. You're able to split hairs. You could say, I watched the
shovel to make sure that it did not become, yes, it wasn't
that I didn't watch the shovel at all. I watched the shovel
to make sure that it did not become a ראשון. rishon. But
I didn't watch it to make sure it didn't become a שני.
sheni. Okay, so if the shovel is טמא, it's only a low
level of טומאה. And that low level of טומאה will not create
a problem with my figs. And if my figs are תרומה, trumah,
then I made sure that the shovel didn't become a שני sheni
so it won't make my figs into a שלישי. shlishi, You got
it? So basically what רבא's Rava saying is I know the case
is, I know I got a shovel in there with figs and
I don't want the figs to become טמא. So I'm going to
watch the shovel not, watch it
vigilantly, but I'm going to watch it well enough to make sure
that if it becomes טמא, it won't be a טומאה that can
affect my figs. So if my figs are a שלישי, shlishi I'm
going to, are תרומה, trumah. I'm going to make sure the shovel
doesn't become a שני. sheni. And if my figs are חולין, chulin
I'm going to make sure that the shovel
doesn't become a,
wait a minute,
does that work? Yes, doesn't become a ראשון. rishon. Okay, so anyway,
so basically you see that somebody can say, I am watching my
shovel and I will allow, it might allow it to become a
certain level of טומאה, but not a טומאה that will be enough
of a problem to, to make the figs a problem. I won't
let it become a ראשון rishon or a שני. sheni. If it's
going to be a problem, it'll be a שלישי shlishi. or whatever.
Okay, so that shows us that you can split hairs. And therefore
we're going to say the same thing here. You can make, the
אונן onen can make sure that he's going to, that the, if
he becomes טמא, it'll only be a טומאה that'll affect him for
קרבנות, korbanot, not a טומאה that'll affect him for תרומה. trumah All
right, so anyway, that's a very, very complicated and difficult answer to
explain all of this evidence by אונן. onen And now the גמרא
Gemara gives a much simpler answer to this. Okay. איגליא מילתא, igalya
milsa, the discussion rolled around, okay, funny interesting phrase, the discussion sort
of rolled around, ומטי לקמיה דרבי אבא בר ממל, umatei lekamei de-Rabbi
Abba bar Mamal, it came before רבי אבא בר ממל. Rabbi Abba
bar Mamal. אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבי אבא בר ממל Rabbi
Abba bar Mamal said, לא שמיע להו, lo shamia lehu, I don't
understand, all these rabbis are trying to figure out this אונן onen
thing, they're doing these crazy somersaults to explain how come our משנה
mishnah says you can touch and all this other evidence says you
can't, and they talk about different levels of היסח הדעת. hesech hadaat.
There's a much easier answer to all this guys. לא שמיע להו,
lo shamia lehu, didn't they...? Here, הא דאמר רבי יוחנן אמר רב
האוכל שלישי של תרומה. ha d'amar Rabbi Yochanan amar Rav ha'ochel shlishi
shel trumah.
Let's say somebody eats something that is תרומה trumah, that is a
שלישי. shlishi What's his status? So normally a שלישי shlishi, doesn't affect
my status if I touch it. But if you eat it, חז"ל
chazal were strict and they said if you ate a שלישי, shlishi,
you know the principle you are what you eat? That's this. Okay,
if you ate a שלישי, shlishi. you became a שלישי. shlishi, Is
that a rabbinic stringency? Oh yeah, it's all, this is all rabbinic.
האוכל שלישי של תרומה אסור לאכול. ha'ochel shlishi shel trumah assur l'echol.
Okay, so now you can't go ahead and, okay, and you are
not allowed to eat תרומה, trumah okay. He was already prohibited from
eating the טמא תרומה. tamei trumah. Right, right,
well, when, well yeah, but
well that's true, no, well, if the תרומה trumah. is, he can't
eat.
That's true, that is correct, you can't be eating the תרומה. trumah.
Anyway, but okay. Anyway, so,
okay, one minute. So it's actually a little bit funny, I was
just processing, if somebody ate a שלישי, shlishi they are not allowed
to eat a שלישי shlishi, now. That's a little bit funny because
even if you are what you eat and even if you ate
a שלישי, shlishi, you became a שלישי, shlishi a שלישי shlishi, can
actually touch תרומה. trumah Okay, so it's like A, you are what
you eat and B, I guess you eat is what you are,
sort of it's all the same, I guess that's right. So the
same way when you ate a שלישי, shlishi, you became a שלישי,
shlishi, don't eat תרומה trumah because by eating תרומה trumah you'll, again
this is all very rabbinically, you are what you eat and what
you eat is what you are, you'll make the תרומה trumah like
a שלישי, shlishi, okay. It's all rabbinic, okay. So, and you've just
violated דאורייתא de'oraita by eating the טמא תרומה. tamei trumah. Oh, we're
fine, we're not going to, we're going to ignore that. Okay, but
you ate a שלישי, shlishi it could also be you ate חולין
that was treated as if it were תרומה trumah, which can become
a שלישי shlishi without violating. So, but you are correct, you were
not supposed to do that. Okay, but you ate a שלישי shlishi
of תרומה, trumah you become a שלישי shlishi. in the sense of
don't eat תרומה trumah because then it'll also make the תרומה trumah
שלישי. shlishi, But all this is only through an act of eating.
This eating creates this total identification and it doesn't go down a
level. One minute. You don't go down a level from what you
ate and what you ate doesn't go down a level from what
you are. That's point number one. But אסור לאכול ומותר ליגע, assur
l'echol u'mutar liga,
but you are allowed to touch תרומה trumah because even if you're
a שלישי, shlishi, if it's just by touch, touch does go down
a level and תרומה trumah, can't become a רביעי. revi'i. So what
you see is there's a special rule about eating. When you eat
something טמא, it gives you the same level and if you eat
something טהור, it transfers the same level to the thing that you
ate. Okay, but that's only about eating, that's not about touch. Got
it? So even though you ate this שלישי, shlishi, okay, even if
we treat you as a שלישי, shlishi, you can touch תרומה, trumah.
just don't eat תרומה. trumah Once we see this, it explains everything.
Okay, so, so אלמא באכילה עבדו רבנן מעלה בנגיעה לא עבדו רבנן
מעלה. alma b'achila avdu rabanan maalah b'negiah lo avdu rabanan maalah.
It's all about eating, it's not about touching. So our משנה Mishna
that said that you can touch is a normal אונן, onen. a
normal אונן, onen, it's not because you were super careful. You're a
normal אונן onen and go ahead and touch. Okay, no problem touching.
Okay, but the same normal אונן, onen, forget all this היסח הדעת
hesach hadaat discussion and then we'd have to say you have a,
you have a very fine-tuned היסח הדעת hesach hadaat that you're careful
of this. No היסח הדעת. hesach hadaat. A normal אונן, onen. no
היסח הדעת. hesach hadaat. He can touch, but don't eat. Okay, and
a normal אונן onen we're going to treat him
like a rabbinic שלישי, shlishi like this guy who ate this טמא
תרומה. tamei trumah. He's a rabbinic שלישי shlishi when it comes to
eating. So you can touch it or whatever, but don't eat it,
okay. And
the whole thing about going to the מקווה mikvah and the whole
thing and you still, and so on, all of that is for
this rabbinic status that an אונן onen cannot eat קדשים, kodshim, okay.
He can eat תרומה trumah, but he can't eat קדשים. kodshim. So
he effectively is a,
just like this guy who ate this תרומה, trumah, he effectively, well
actually he's more, he's more like a רביעי revi'i I guess. He
is sort of like a rabbinic, so if it's real היסח הדעת
hesach hadaat that's three and seven. This is not היסח הדעת hesach
hadaat at all. This guy is like a rabbinic רביעי revi'i or
as it were. So a rabbinic רביעי, revi'i, okay, got it? A
rabbinic רביעי revi'i can touch קדשים, kodshim, a שלישי shlishi can't touch
קדשים. kodshim. But the same way a rabbinic שלישי can't eat תרומה,
trumah, a rabbinic רביעי, revi'i, this אונן onen can't eat קדשים. kodshim.
Okay, so the משנה Mishna. that says that says that this אונן
onen is טמא and even if he goes to the מקווה mikvah
it's still going to go back to being טמא, right, that whole
description that he's going to be טמא the whole day and so
on, it's not because of split levels of היסח הדעת. hesach hadaat.
It's because no, a normal אונן onen has these two הלכות: halachot:
go be געזונטהייט, gezuntheit, touch, but don't eat. You can eat תרומה,
don't eat קדשים. kodshim. And if you go to the מקוה, it
doesn't help, it's going to circle back on you. Very, very simple.
So that really simplified all of that. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues: ואינו חולק לאכול. v’eino cholek l’echol. So we’re not done
yet fully with an אונן, onen we’re going to come back to
him, but at least we figured out this basic issue of his
status. Okay, so he is allowed to touch, as we just clarified,
he's not allowed to eat, that was this whole point, and because
he wasn't allowed to do the עבודה avodah. and he wasn't allowed
to eat, he's not entitled to a portion. We're back to that.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מפלג הוא דלא פליג.
miflag hu d’lo palig. Okay, he doesn't get a portion that night.
וכי מזמני ליה אכיל, v’chi mazmni lei achil, but if they invited
him, he would be allowed to eat that night, right? That's פשט
pshat of the משנה, Mishna that an אונן onen can't do the
עבודה avodah. and can't eat during the day, but at night he's
allowed to eat, but because he was excluded in the day, he
doesn't get a portion. So now we're going to focus in on
that. Is this true that an אונן onen is allowed to eat
קרבנות korbanot at night? That's pretty implicit in the משנה, Mishna. is
that actually true that an אונן onen is allowed to eat קרבנות
korbanot, the night following the death? He's still אונן. onen Well, no,
that's the question. I mean, again, not the אנינות aninus we talk
about about פטור from מצוות mitzvot or whatever. An אנינות aninus that
excludes him from קרבנות, korbanot, that's our
question. Okay, but there's קבורת המת kvuras hameis or am I thinking
of the wrong? Well, it's the same point, so was there a
קבורה, kvura, we're going to bracket that for now. Okay? Maybe yes,
maybe no, but it is the night following the death. Okay, yes,
let us assume, we'll clarify in a minute, let us assume that
today, Monday, the father died and was buried today, he has a
status of אונן onen for all of Monday day and he can't
do the עבודה, avodah, right? Only a כהן kohen, גדול is allowed
to do the עבודה, avodah, he is excluded from the עבודה. avodah.
Okay, he might be excluded from eating קרבנות korbanot because of this
whole rabbinic thing, but he's excluded from the עבודה. avodah, He doesn't
get a portion. Okay, at night, okay,
but presumably by night he is at least no longer an אונן
onen in terms of eating and he is allowed to, the next
day he'll be able to do the עבודה, avodah, at that night
he could do the עבודה, avodah he could maybe burn the אימורין
emurin that night. His whole אנינות status that excludes him, the תורה
Torah is clear that an אונן onen doesn't do the עבודה. avoda
Okay, so that אנינות status that excludes him, we're going to assume
it was the death and burial the same day, that applies during
the day, it doesn't apply at night. So at least that's the
assumption. At night he can do the עבודה, avoda you want to
go ahead and burn the אימורין, emurin, and at night you're allowed
to eat the קרבנות korbanot and so on, it only applied during
the day. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says like this, but
now we're going to look into that. מפלג הוא דלא פליג וכי
מזמני ליה אכיל, miflag hu d’lo palig v’chi mazmni lei achil, but
if they invited him he'd be allowed to eat. Okay, ורמינהי, I’ll
ask you on this. We have in פסחים: Psachim: אונן טובל ואוכל
את פסחו לערב. onen tovel v’ochel es pischo l’erev.
An אונן onen can go ahead and go to the מקוה and
eat his קרבן פסח korban pesach that night. Okay, so guy became
an אונן onen ערב פסח. erev pesach. Okay, he wants to be
able to eat his פסח pesach that night. So we allow him
to do that. Go to the מקוה because we just spoke about
this אונן onen having some rabbinic status of טומאה, go to the
מקוה and then go ahead that night and you'll be able to
eat your קרבן פסח, korban pesach, no problem. Okay, so you see
you are allowed to eat קרבנות korbanot at night. But, אבל לא
בקדשים. aval lo b’kodshim.
That's a special allowance we make by קרבן פסח, korban pesach, not
by קרבנות. korbanot. Now, the fact that we're allowing it by קרבן
פסח korban pesach and not by other קרבנות korbanos. means that this
is only rabbinic. Okay, this not eating, that's what we just got
through saying. Again, the אונן onen, in the תורה Torah is about
not doing the עבודה, avoda, but the not eating seems to be
only rabbinic. Okay, but at least what you see is, so rabbinically,
we don't let you eat קרבנות korbanos, the night following, but we'll
waive it for the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. Okay, but at least
rabbinically we don't let you eat. So why does our משנה Mishna
imply that that night, if they gave him from some of their
steak, he is allowed to join in with the steak that night?
At least at a rabbinic level it shouldn't be allowed. Okay,
that's the question. אמר רבי ירמיה מדיפתי: amar rabbi yirmiyah midifti: לא
קשיא, it's not difficult. כאן בפסח כאן בשאר ימות השנה. kan b’pesach
kan b’sh'ar yemos hashana. Okay, no.
When is he allowed to eat that night, like when was our
משנה Mishna be talking about? Our משנה mishna. would be talking about,
it's a little bizarre to say this is our משנה, mishna on
פסח Pesach itself. On פסח Pesach itself, he is allowed
to. פסח איידי דאכיל פסח אכיל נמי קדשים. pesach ayidi d’achil pesach
achil nami kodshim. Since we're waiving his status for eating פסח, Pesach,
we'll allow him to eat other קרבנות. korbanot So our משנה mishna
that implies that an אונן onen can eat at night is the
night of the סדר. seder. Who knew we were talking about the
night of the
סדר? seder? Okay, but בשאר ימות השנה דלא חזי לא חזי. b’sh'ar
yemos hashana d’lo chazi lo chazi. When we say that an אונן
onen can't eat at night, at least rabbinically, that is any night
that's not the סדר seder night, but the סדר seder night we
give him a blanket allowance. So this is another example of a
positive overriding?
No, we're not, well, this is all rabbinic. We're not framing it
that way. Maybe you could, but that's not the way we're framing
it, okay? We're seeing this all as a rabbinic issue and then
we're deciding to waive it or not waive
it. ומה אבל לא בקדשים uma aval lo b’kodshim
so what does it mean the— The משנה mishna in פסחים Pesachim
that says an אונן onen can’t eat קדשים, kodashim, based on what
we said you can eat קדשים kodashim on סדר Seder night. It
means ומה דלא בקדשים שכל השנה U-ma d'lo b'kodashim shekol hashana during
the rest of the year you can't eat קדשים. kodashim. Okay? So
that’s a very, very weak אוקימתא okimta of our משנה. mishna Our
משנה that implies that an אונן onen can eat at night, we’re
saying means the סדר Seder night. Who knew? Okay. רב אשי אמר
לא קשיא. Rav Ashi amar lo kashya.
No, no, no. And now it gets to חנן’s Chanan point. כאן
שמת מתו בארבעה עשר וקברו בארבעה עשר. Kan she-meito met b'arba'asar v'kivro
b'arba'asar. When do we say that there’s an אנינות status in the
Torah? The אנינות status in the Torah is when the מיתה misa
and the קבורה kvura were on the same day. Okay? So if
the guy was died and buried on the same day, then he’s
a biblical אונן. onen. Okay? And therefore, and therefore if he’s a
biblical אונן, onen. we’re going to extend that into the night and
say rabbinically we’re going to extend the eating thing into the night
and say ah, you were a biblical אונן onen today, tonight you’re
not allowed to eat קרבנות korbanot with the exception of פסח. Pesach.
Okay? But if somebody was not a biblical אונן, onen. כאן שמת
מתו בשלושה עשר וקברו בארבעה עשר. Kan she-meito met bishlosha asar v'kivro
b'arba'asar. Today is the 14th ערב פסח. erev Pesach. Today the guy
buried his father, but it’s not the day of death. And if
it’s not the day of death, then it is not a biblical
אונן. onen Okay, he’s only a דרבנן derabbanan אונן onen if if
if it wasn't the day of death. Okay,
so יום קבורה לא תפיס לילה מדרבנן. Yom kvura lo tafis leilo
mi-derabbanan. So when the whole אנינות is דרבנן, derabbanan, the night is
not. Okay, so now
let’s draw this out here. Okay, so here we have
13, 14 and סדר Seder night. The night of the סדר. Seder.
Okay so here if
the guy... you're going to love my little thing, like little x's
in his eyes. The guy dies on the 13th, is buried on
the 14th, like my little pictograms. Okay so in this case,
okay, he’s an אונן onen דאורייתא d'oraita on the day of death,
he’s an אונן onen דרבנן derabbanan this day which is not the
day of death, and because he’s an אונן onen, דרבנן, derabbanan, the
night of the סדר Seder is or any night... let’s just say
the whatever... you know, the point here is the following night. In
our case it is. I mean, again you know if it's פסח
Pesach it’s פסח, Pesach, but the following night he is basically
not an אונן onen. even דרבנן derabbanan because he was only an
אונן onen דרבנן derabbanan here so we’re not going to extend it
here and therefore he can eat קדשים. kodashim. And that’s our case
in our משנה. Okay? And it didn’t have to be 13 and
14. Basically the case in our משנה was the night following a
case where he was only an אונן onen דרבנן. derabbanan. All right?
So therefore since the dead body hadn’t been buried here he was
not allowed to do the עבודה avoda, in this case, he wasn’t
allowed to eat קרבנות, korbanos okay, but that’s only at a דרבנן
derabbanan level, okay, and therefore the night following and then he got
buried so now we’re moving on so the night following he is
actually going to be allowed to eat. So that’s our משנה that
the night following is allowed to eat. In the case however where
he was died on the
right on the 14th and he’s an אונן onen דאורייתא d'oraita
and maybe he was also buried that day. This
is fun. Okay anyway okay so he’s an אונן onen דאורייתא d'oraita
so here he’s an אונן onen דרבנן derabbanan and therefore the night
and therefore what we’re going to say is eat the פסח Pesach
but don't eat other קדשים. kodashim.
Okay? Got it? So that’s what the גמרא Gemara says. Now
where were we? Okay now
okay
so יום קבורה לא תפיס לילה מדרבנן. Yom kvura lo tafis leilo
mi-derabbanan. Okay if the יום קבורה yom kvura is rabbinic
meaning it’s a יום קבורה, yom kvura, it’s not a יום מיתה,
yom misa, יום מיתה yom misa grabs the following night. The יום
קבורה yom kvura doesn’t grab the following night. Okay. מאן תנא אנינות
לילה מדרבנן? Man tana aninus layla mi-derabbanan? Now who is the תנא
tanna that says that the night is only rabbinic? The fact that
we’re allowing it for a פסח Pesach and not for other קרבנות
korbanot even in this case where the day you were דאורייתא d'oraita
means that the night at most it's only rabbinic, right? That’s this
case. Okay and therefore because and that's why we’re allowing it for
the פסח Pesach and not for other things. Who is that? מדרבי
שמעון היא. Mi-derabbi Shimon hi. It’s רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דתניא אנינות
לילה מדברי תורה דברי רבי יהודה. De-tanya aninus layla midivrei Torah divrei
Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no no no the אנינות
status extends into the night even from the Torah’s perspective. רבי שמעון
אומר אין אונן מדברי תורה אלא מדברי סופרים. Rabbi Shimon omer ein
onen midivrei Torah ela midivrei sofrim. Now he can’t mean that... death.
Now he can't mean that אנינות is completely, right, you know, מדרבנן.
miderabbanan. It means in this case of אנינות לילה aninus layla that
we're talking about. Nighttime אנינות is only rabbinic if it's not the
day of the
death. תדע, teda, and his proof is this משנה. So it's funny,
it's like this משנה was taught by רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, this
משנה was a משנה presumably that, you know, was passed down and
he's saying this משנה shows my position: אונן טובל ואוכל פסחו לערב
אבל לא בקדשים. onen tovel v'ochel pisho l'erev aval lo b'kodashim. So
you see if we're letting him eat a קרבן פסח korban Pesach
that night, it clearly is not a biblical status. Now, I have
to tell you a funny thing because
we're now conflating the אונן onen as somebody who can do the
עבודה and somebody who can eat קרבנות, korbanos, okay? Because why doesn't
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda come back and say like the eating קרבנות,
korbanot, that's rabbinic, that's why I'll let him eat the קרבן פסח.
korban Pesach. There's another question of an אונן onen status in terms
of doing the עבודה and other types of things, etc., etc. So
right now we're like conflating it all. Although before we said the
whole eating thing was a- was rabbinic, now we're ignoring that difference
and assuming all the laws of אונן in one basket. Okay. So
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying the fact that an אונן eats
the קרבן פסח korban Pesach that night shows me nighttime is only
rabbinic. That's his point. Okay. And therefore we waive it for קרבן
פסח. korban Pesach. Okay. Now, וסבר רבי שמעון אנינות לילה מדרבנן? v'savar
Rabbi Shimon aninus layla miderabbanan? So it doesn't tell us how רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would respond to that. Maybe רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would disagree, would say you can't eat the קרבן פסח korban Pesach
that night. But now we're going to question this: Does רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon really hold it's only rabbinic? והתניא, v'hatanya, we got a
ברייתא: braita: רבי שמעון אומר אונן אינו משלח קרבנותיו. Rabbi Shimon omer
onen eino meshale'ach korbanotav. An אונן can't have somebody bring his קרבנות
for him in order to allow him to eat that night. Now,
big deal. He said that you can't eat normal קרבנות that night.
So the גמרא's Gemara, question, this is a very weak question: מאי
לאו אפילו בפסח? mai lav afilu b'Pesach? Oh, doesn't that mean somebody
can't even bring a קרבן פסח korban Pesach for you? Which is
so bizarre, right? If it's not saying פסח, Pesach, what would make
you think it would include it? לא לבר מפסח. lo levar miPesach.
Okay, no, he means he can't bring other קרבנות because he does
agree מדרבנן miderabbanan you can't eat that night. Okay, so fine, that
wasn't really a proof. But here's the problem. והתניא, v'hatanya, we got
a ברייתא: braita: רבי שמעון אומר שלמים, Rabbi Shimon omer shelamim, it
says: ואם זבח שלמים קרבנו, v'im zevach shelamim korbano, כשהוא שלם מביא
ואינו מביא כשהוא אונן. keshehu shalem mevi v'eino mevi keshehu onen. That-
now this is a fascinating new הלכה. halacha. The תורה's Torah only
clear that an אונן can't do the עבודה, right? רבי שמעון's Rabbi
Shimon דרשה drasha is: You have to be in a state of
completeness when you're bringing a קרבן, korban and if you are, you
know, somehow in this state of distance from God or feeling shattered
or whatever it is because you're an אונן, right, we don't do
a psychological work-up before you're allowed into the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash
you know, but it's somebody who we can assume his status is
one who's like just suffered a tremendous tragic loss. That is not
a person who should be bringing a קרבן. korban. So אונן not
only excludes you from doing the עבודה, it excludes you from bringing
a קרבן. korban It's fascinating, right? So first of all, it's sort
of like the person who feels like, oh, I am- I'm so
messed up, I'll get married, it'll solve all my problems, you know?
It's like no, you have to like come in a little bit
being okay, you know, in order to develop the relationship. Or the
other point is like the fact that רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik explained
that the reason an אונן doesn't do מצוות mitzvot, is not just
because עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה. osek bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah. He
said the reason an אונן doesn't do מצוות, mitzvot somebody who suffered
such a tragic loss, we need to almost like not force him
back into the system. And doing מצוות mitzvot. is like life-affirming. It
says that there's a purpose, it sort of, you know, and allows
you to connect to God and whatever, maybe this person is questioning
whether life has meaning, is que- you know, is feeling very distant
from God and we sort of acknowledge that and allow that to
some degree, almost even enforce that. We don't even let him do
מצוות. mitzvot, We sort of, you know, so same point here like,
you know what? This is not the time for you to be
engaging and bringing קרבנות. Like you got, you know, so it's a-
you're in a different state right now in terms of your relationship
to the world, to a life of מצוות, mitzvos, to relationship with
הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu and so on. Okay. ואינו מביא
כשהוא אונן. v'eino mevi keshehu onen. מנין לרבות את התודה? minayin l'rabot
et hatodah? How do I know an אונן doesn't even bring a
תודה? todah? מרבה אני את התודה. marbeh ani et hatodah. Now, that's
logical to include. שכן נאכלת בשמחה כשלמים. sheken ne'echelet besimcha keshelamim. There's
an idea like a שלמים, shelamim, you bring it as thanksgiving, it's
joy, that's particularly inappropriate for an אונן. He hated the person who
died maybe. Well,
מנין לרבות את העולה? minayin l'rabot et ha'olah? How do you know
to include an עולה, olah, which is not the same, it's not
about eating, right? It's totally about just bringing the קרבן, korban it's
not about joy, it's not about eating. מרבה אני את העולה שכן
באה בנדר ונדבה. marbeh ani et ha'olah sheken ba'ah beneder unedavah. It's
still like an act of generosity and giving to God. It's close
enough and we would say that's inappropriate for somebody who's an אונן.
Okay. מרבה אני את העולה שכן באה בנדר ונדבה כשלמים. marbeh ani
et ha'olah sheken ba'ah beneder unedavah keshelamim. מנין לרבות בכור מעשר ופסח?
minayin l'rabot bechor ma'aser u'Pesach? How do I know to include these
things which are sort of like שלמים shelamim but they're obligatory? מרבה
אני בכור מעשר ופסח שכן אינם באים על חטא. marbeh ani bechor
ma'aser u'Pesach sheken einam ba'im al chet. At least they're not about
sin, so they're still seen as just a normal way of connecting
which doesn't have like a weighty negative. valence to it, okay. And
therefore you shouldn't be doing that as an אונן either. מר מניין
לרבות חטאת ואשם? Mar minayin le-rabos chatas ve-asham? How about things that
are about sin? Maybe you know when you suffer a loss that
makes you very self-reflective, what did I do to deserve it, maybe
sin is exactly an appropriate type of thing? תלמוד לומר זבח אם
זבח שלמים קרבנו. Talmud lomar zevach im zevach shelamim korbano. So the
idea of שלמים shelamim applies to every זבח, zevach, every animal sacrifice.
Okay, מניין לרבות העופות והמנחות והיין והעצים והלבונה? minayin le-rabos ha-ofos ve-ha-menachos
ve-ha-yayin ve-ha-eitzim ve-ha-levona? How about these other types of offerings that you
can donate and bring which are not about slaughtering, which are not
these big animal sacrifices? תלמוד לומר שלמים קרבנו. Talmud lomar shelamim korbano.
So זבח שלמים, zevach shelamim, any זבח zevach you have to be
שלם, shalem, and שלמים קרבנו, shelamim korbano, any קרבן korban you bring
you have to be שלם. shalem. כל הקרבנות כשהוא מביא כשהוא שלם
מביא ואינו מביא כשהוא אונן. Kol ha-korbanot keshu mevi keshu shalem mevi
ve-eino mevi keshu onen. Okay, so it's a very beautiful, it's a
new idea of אונן. אונן is not just excluding you from the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, as a כהן, this is not the time,
it's very consistent with not the time to do מצוות, you are
not שלם shalem right now, this is not the time to be
bringing קרבנות. Now okay, that's all very nice, but what does he
say? An אונן can't bring a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, can't have
somebody bring a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach for him. So how could
the same רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon say an אונן brings a קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach and eats it that night? Now we're not so
much focusing on the night and the eating the night, we're like
what's the scenario that you brought it in the day? You just
said that an אונן is excluded from bringing a קרבן. korban Okay,
good question. Okay, קתני מיהת פסח? Kasani mi-has pesach? Ah, it says
פסח. pesach. אמר רב חסדא פסח כדי נסבה. Amar Rav Chisda pesach
kedi nasba. Yeah, that was just thrown in, that we didn't mean
it. Like בכור מעשר, bechor maaser, which makes sense, it really does.
Like בכור מעשר פסח bechor maaser pesach is just like your standard
when you're working your way through the קרבנות, you get to בכור
מעשר פסח. bechor maaser pesach. But in practice, פסח pesach we would
let you bring, okay. Which is interesting because now it's not just
we'd let you eat that night, right? We'd let you bring and
we ignore this concern of כשהוא שלם. keshu shalem. So what's the
idea of ignoring... if there's a real תורה concern of כשהוא שלם,
keshu shalem, what lets us bring the פסח pesach during the day?
You understand the question? So there's two answers. רש"י Rashi says this
whole big beautiful דרשה drasha was all an אסמכתא. asmachta. Okay, that's
a pretty weak answer. תוספות Tosafos says, this is very important, pay
attention, תוספות Tosafos says, oh I've made this point before, all the
other קרבנות the focus is on the bringing of the קרבן korban
and the זריקת הדם. zrikas ha-dam. The פסח, pesach, what's the entire
focus on? Eating. The only reason you bring it is to enable
you to eat it, which is why all the קרבנות that are
brought בטומאה, be-tumah, you don't eat them בטומאה, be-tumah, with the exception
of פסח. pesach. פסח pesach is all about the eating. So תוספות
Tosafos says it here, it's brilliant. תוספות Tosafos says, no, there is
a תורה הלכה Torah halacha of כשהוא שלם. keshu shalem. Okay? But
that's when the bringing of the קרבן is your focus and it's
being brought when you're an אונן, you're not allowed to bring it.
פסח, pesach, the bringing is just a way of allowing you to
eat that night. So we don't focus on were you שלם shalem
when the blood was thrown? The focus is on your eating at
night and your eating at night you're not going to be an
אונן. So the fact that it had to get brought today or
whatever, the concept of being שלם shalem at that time or whatever
was not relevant because the focus of the קרבן was not the
bringing of it. Very beautiful explanation, okay. So the גמרא says, yeah,
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon basically has an idea an אונן can't have
a קרבן brought for him but it doesn't apply to a פסח,
pesach, okay, כדי נסבה. kedi nasba. Okay, רב ששת אמר, Rav Sheshes
amar, well I know we're a little over but let's just read
this one more answer. רב ששת אמר מאי פסח שלמי פסח. Rav
Sheshes amar mai pesach shalmei pesach. When it says an אונן can't
have a פסח pesach brought, it means he can't bring the קרבנות
that go with the פסח, pesach, the שלמים shelamim or whatever. So
it's still the same basic answer, an אונן can have a פסח
pesach brought for him. אי הכי Ei hachi says the גמרא, היינו
שלמים? hainu shelamim? We already said an אונן can't bring
שלמים. shelamim. תנא שלמים הבאים מחמת הפסח ותנא שלמים הבאים מחמת עצמן.
Tana shelamim ha-baim machmas ha-pesach ve-tana shelamim ha-baim machmas atzman. Okay, it
says both two types of שלמים. shelamim. You can't bring סתם שלמים
stam shelamim and you can't bring an אונן שלמים onen shelamim that
comes for the
פסח. pesach. דאי לא תנא שלמים הבאים מחמת הפסח, De-it lo tana
shelamim ha-baim machmas ha-pesach, if it had not said that category, סלקא
דעתך אמינא, salka datach amina, I would have thought, הואיל ומחמת הפסח
אתי, holeil umachmas ha-pesach asi, maybe if it's coming because of the
פסח, pesach, like the חגיגה chagiga that comes with the פסח pesach
that allows you to eat the פסח pesach when you're full, so
maybe it's all one big package. Maybe כגופיה דפסח דמי, ke-gufeih de-pesach
dami, maybe the same way we let you bring a פסח pesach
we let this אונן bring the חגיגה that comes with a פסח.
pesach. קא משמע לן Kamashmalan he can't. Okay, but in the end
everybody agrees רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says he's got this great דרשה
drasha that an אונן can't have a קרבן brought for him even
without him entering the בית המקדש, he's not שלם, shalem, but he
can have a פסח pesach brought for him. And תוספות Tosafos again
explains because the focus of the פסח pesach is night. And as
far as eating קרבנות at night, he says an אונן status of
night is rabbinic, not to eat קרבנות, okay, and therefore that applies
to all other קרבנות, but the פסח, pesach, okay, that we are
going to waive it because nighttime is only rabbinic and we're going
to let him eat the פסח, pesach, okay. And that's רבי שמעון's
Rebbi Shimon position and we will continue with this on שבת. Shabbos.